all right everyone thanks for coming in
this is the missing semester of your CS Education
at least that's what we chose to call
the class if you're not here for this
class then you're in the wrong room we
will be here for about an hour just to
set your expectations and I want to talk
to you a little bit first about why
we're doing this class so this class
stems out of an observation that Anish
and Jose and I have made while TA-ing various
classes at MIT which is that basically
all of us computer scientists we know
that computers are great at doing these
repetitive tasks and automating things
but we often fail to realize that there
are lots of tools that can make our own
development processes better we can be a
lot more efficient about how we use our
computers because we can use the
computer as a tool for ourselves not
just for building websites or software
those sorts of things and this class is
an attempt to address this is an attempt
to show you some of the tools that you
can use to great effect in your day to
day in your research and in your studies
and it's going to be a class where we
want you to teach you both how to make
the most of the tools that you already
know but also hopefully teach you about
some tools so you don't know from before
and how to combine those tools to
produce more powerful things than you
think you might be able to do with what
you know today the class is going to be
structured as a series of 11 one-hour
lectures and each one is going to cover
a particular topic you can see the
website which is also listed there for
the list of lecture topics and what date
will do each one they will mostly be
independent and so you can sort of show
up for the ones that you're interested
in but we will sort of assume that
you've been following along so that as
we get to later lectures I'm not going
to be teaching you bash all over again
for example we we are also going to post
both the lecture notes and recordings of
the lectures online exactly when we do
that we haven't established yet but it
will be after the lectures obviously the
videos have to be posted after
the class is gonna be run by me John and
Anne each sitting over there and Jose
who is not currently here but we'll be
holding tomorrow's lecture and keep in
mind that we're trying to cover a lot of
ground over the course of just 11
one-hour lectures and so we will be
moving relatively rapidly but please do
stop us if there's anything where you
feel like you're not following along if
you feel like there's something you wish
we would spend more time on just let us
know please interrupt us with questions
and also after each lecture we're going
to hold office hours on the ninth floor
of building 30 to the Stata Center of
the computer science building as if you
show up up in the ninth floor lounge
there and the gates tower then you can
come and try some of the exercises that
we give for each lecture or just ask us
other questions about things we've
talked about in lecturer or other things
about using your computer efficiently
due to the limited time that we have
available we're not going to be able to
cover all tools and full detail and so
we'll try to do is highlight interesting
tools and interesting ways to use them
we won't necessarily dig into the deep
details about how all of it works or
more elaborate use cases but if you have
questions about them please come ask us
about that too many of these tools are
tools that we have used for years and we
might be able to point you to additional
interesting things you can do with them
sort of like take advantage of the fact
that we're here this class is going to I
don't wanna say ramped up quickly but
what's going to happen over the course
of this particular lecture is that we'll
cover many of the basics that we assume
that you will know for the rest of the
semester things like how to use your
shell and your terminal and I'll explain
what those are - those who you're not
familiar with them and then will pretty
quickly ramp up into more advanced tools
and how to use them you can already see
from the lecture notes the kind of
topics that we're going to be covering
and so that brings us to today's lecture
in which we are going to cover the shell
and the shell is going to be one of the
primary ways that you interact with your
computer once you want to do more things
than what the sort of visual interfaces
you might be used to allow you to do the
visual interfaces are sort of limited in
what
they allow you to do because you can
only do the things that there are
buttons for sliders for input fields for
often these textual tools are built to
be both composable with one another but
also to have tons of different ways to
combine them or ways to program and
automate them and that is why in this
class we will be focusing on these
command line or text-based tools and the
shell is the place that you would do
most of this work so for those of you
are not familiar with the shell most
platform provides some kind of shell on
Windows this is often PowerShell but
there are also other shells available on
Windows on Linux you will find tons of
terminals these are windows that allow
you to display shells and you'll also
find many different types of shells the
most common of which is bash or the born
again shell because it's such a common
shell it is the one we're primarily
going to be covering in these lectures
if you're on Mac OS you will probably
also have bash maybe an older version of
it if you open the terminal app and so
if you want to follow along on any of
these platforms feel free but keep in
mind that most of this is going to be
sort of Linux centric in terms of how we
teach it even though most of these tools
work on all the platforms if you want to
install a terminal and a shell and you
don't know how to do it well we're happy
to show you at office hours or it's
usually very easy to just Google like
your platform plus like terminal and you
will get one now when you open a
terminal you get something that looks a
little bit like this so it will usually
have just a single line at the top and
this is what's known as the shell prompt
you can see that my shell prompt looks
like this it has my user name the name
of the machine that I'm on the current
path I'm on and we will talk about paths
a little bit later and then it's really
just sort of blinking they're asking me
for input and this is the shell prompt
where you tell the shell what you want
it to do and you can customize this
prompt a lot and when you open it on
your machine it might not look exactly
like this it might look something like
this if you've configured it a little or
it might look all sorts of different
ways we won't go too much into
customizing your shell in this
particularly
we'll do that later here we're just
going to talk about how do you use this
shell to do useful things and this is
our the main textual interface you have
to your computer's through this shell on
the shell prompt you get to write
commands and commands can be relatively
straightforward things usually it'll be
something like executing programs with
arguments what does that look like well
one program we can execute is the date
program we just type date and press
enter and then it will show you
unsurprisingly the date and time you can
also execute a program with arguments
this is one way to modify the behavior
of the program so for example there is a
program called echo and echo just prints
out the arguments that you give it and
arguments are just white space separated
things that follow the program name so
we can say hello and then it will print
hello back
perhaps not terribly surprising but this
is the very basics of arguments one
thing that you'll notice is that I said
that arguments are separated by
whitespace and you might wonder well
what if I want an argument as multiple
words you can also quote things so you
can do things like echo hello space
world and now the echo program receives
one argument that contains the string
hello world with a space well you can
also use single quotes for this and the
difference between single quotes and
double quotes will get back to and when
we talk about bash scripting you can
also just escape single characters so
for example hello world this will also
work just fine all of these rules about
how you escape and how you parse and
quote various arguments and variables
we'll cover a little bit later hopefully
you won't run into too many we oughta
tease about this just keep in mind at
least that spaces separate arguments so
if you want to do something like make a
directory called my photos
you can't just type like make directory
my photos it will create two directories
one called my and one called photos and
that is probably not what you want now
one thing you might ask is how does the
shell know what these programs are when
I type date or when I type echo how does
it know what these programs are supposed
to do and the answer to this is your
program your
computer has a bunch of built-in
programs that comes with the machine
just like you your machine my chip with
like the terminal app or it might chip
with like Windows Explorer or at my chip
with some kind of browser it also ships
with a bunch of terminal centric
applications and these are stored on
your file system and your shell has a
way to determine where a program is
located basically has a way to search
for programs it does this through
something called an invariant
environment variable an environment
variable is a variable like you might be
used to for programming languages it
turns out that the shell and the
bourne-again shell in particular is
really a programming language this
prompt that you're given here is not
just able to run a program with
arguments you can also do things like
while loops for loops conditionals
all of these that you can define
functions you can of variables and all
of these things you can do in the shell
will cover a lot of that in the next
lecture on shell scripting for now
though let's just look at this
particular environment variable
environment variables are things that
are set whenever you start your shell
they're not things you have to set every
time you run your shell there are a
bunch of these that are set things like
where is your home directory what is
your username and there's also one
that's critical for this particular
purpose which is the path variable so if
I echo out dollar path this is going to
show me all of the paths on my machine
that the shell will search for programs
you'll notice that this is a list that
is colon separated it might be kind of
long and hard to read but the essentials
is that - whenever you type the name of
a program is gonna search through this
list of paths on your machine and it's
gonna look in each directory for a
program or a file whose name matches the
command you try to run so in my case
when I try to run date or echo it's
gonna walk through these one at a time
until it finds one that contains the
program called date or echo and then
it's gonna run it if we want to know
which one it actually runs there's a
command called which which lets us do
that so I can type which echo and will
tell me that if I were to run a program
called echo I would run this one it's
worth pausing here to talk about what
paths are so paths are a way to name the
location of a file on your computer on
Linux and Oh Mac OS these paths are
separated by slashes forward slashes so
you'll see here that this is in the in
the root directory so the slash at the
very beginning indicates that this is
starting from the top of the file system
then look inside the directory called
USR then look inside the directory bin
and then look for the file called echo
on windows paths like this are usually
separated by back slashes instead and
we're on Linux and Mac OS everything
lives under the root name space so all
paths start with a slash or all absolute
paths on Windows there is one root for
every partition so you might have seen
things like C colon backslash or D colon
backslash so Windows has separate sort
of file system path hierarchies for each
each Drive that you have
whereas on Linux and Mac OS these are
all mounted under one namespace you'll
notice that I said the word absolute
path and you might not know what that
means so absolute paths are paths that
fully determine the location of a file
so in this case this is saying this is
talking only about a specific echo file
and it's giving you the the full path to
that file but there are also things
known as relative paths so a relative
path is relative to where you currently
are and so the way we find out where we
currently are is you can type PWD for
present working directory present print
working directory so if I type PWD it
will print out the current path that I'm
in right so currently I'm in the home
directory under the root and then John
under that and then dev under that etc
from here I can then choose to change my
current working directory and all
relative paths are relative to the
current working directory which is
basically where you
they are in this case for example I can
do CD / home CDs change directory this
is the way that I change what my current
working directory is in this case I
change to home and I am now you'll see
my my shell prompt change to say that I
am now in home it just gives me the name
of the last segment of the path but you
can also configure your terminal to give
you the full path whenever you're
anywhere and now if I type PWD again it
will tell me I'm in slash home there are
also a couple of special directories
that exist there is dot and dot dot dot
means the current directory dot dot
means the parent directory so this is a
way that you can easily navigate around
the system for example here if I type CD
dot dot it will tell me that I am now in
slash so I'm now in the root of the file
system I was in slash home now I'm in
slash and indeed if I type PWD well it
will do that right thing and I can also
then use relative paths to go down into
the file system right so I can do CD dot
slash home and this is gonna CD into the
home directory under the current
directory right so this will bring me
back to slash home if I now tried CD dot
slash home again it will say there's no
such directory because there is no home
directory under the current directory
I'm on which I changed by doing CD right
and I can sort of see de all the way
back to the place that I was using
relative paths and I can also do things
like dot dot dot dot dot to get back to
somewhere deep in my file system this
happens to be all the way back to the
root so here there's a bin directory and
another bin there's an echo file and so
then I could do world and that runs the
echo program under bin alright so this
is a way that you can construct paths to
arbitrarily traverse your filesystem
sometimes you want to absolute paths and
sometimes you want relative ones usually
you want to use whichever one is shorter
but if you want to for example run a
program or write
a program that runs the program like
echo or date and you want it to be able
to run be run from anywhere you either
want to just give the name of the
program like date or echo and let the the
shell use the path to figure out where
it is or you want to give its absolute
path because if you gave a relative path
then if I ran it in my home directory
and you ran it in some other directory
it might work for me but not for you in
general when we run a program it is
going to be operating on the current
working directory at least by default
unless we give it any other arguments
and this is really handy because it
means that often we don't have to give
full paths for things we can just use
the name of files and in the directory
that we're currently in one thing that's
really useful is to figure out what is
in the current directory we're in so we
already saw PWD which prints where you
currently are there's a command called
LS which will show you it will list the
files in the current directory so if i
type LS here this is all the files in
the current directory right and this is
a handy way to just quickly navigate
through the filesystem you'll see that
if I sort of CD dot and then do LS it'll
show me the files in that directory
instead but with LS I can also give it
LS dot dot like I can give it a path and
then will LS that file instead of the
one that I'm currently in or LS that
directory and you can see this if I go
all the way to the root as well right
root has different files one handy trick
you might not know about here is there
are two other special things you can do
one is the tilde character this
character brings you to your home
directory so tilde always expands to the
home directory and you can do relative
paths to it so I can do tilde slash dev
slash P DOS classes missing semester and
now I'm there because tilde expanded to
slash home slash John there is also for
CD in particular a really handy argument
you can give which is - if you do CD -
it will CD to the directory you were
previously in so if I do CD - I go back
to root
if I do CD - again I go back to missing
semester so this is a handy way if you
want to toggle between two different
directories in the case of LS or in the
case of CD there might be arguments do
you don't know about right currently we
haven't really been doing anything
except giving paths but how do you even
discover that you can give a path to LS
in the first place well most programs
take what are known as arguments like
flags and options these are things that
usually start with a - one of the Hemi
is one of these is - help most programs
implement this and if you run for
example LS - help it all helpfully print
out a bunch of information about that
command and you'll see here that it says
the usage is LS and you can give some
number of options and you can give some
number of files the way to read that
usage line is triple dot means one like
zero or one or more and the square
bracket means optional so in this case
there's an optional number of options
and there's an optional number of files
and you'll see that it says what the
program does and also specifies a number
of different types of flags and options
you can give usually we call things that
are a single dash in a single letter a
flag and anything that or anything that
doesn't take a value a flag and anything
that does take a value an option so for
example - a and - all are both flags and
- C or - color R is an option one thing
you'll see under here if you scroll down
far enough is the - L flag and that's
unhelpful the - L flag the - L flag uses
a long listing format now that's
particularly helpful in and of itself
but let's see what it actually does so
if I do LS dash L it still prints the
files in the current directory but it
gives me a lot more information about
those files and this is something you'll
find yourself using quite a lot because
the additional information it gives you
is often quite handy let's look at what
some of that information
ah so first of all the D at the
beginning of some of these entries
indicate that something is a directory
so the underscore data entry here for
example is a directory
whereas for for hTML is not a directory
it's a file the following letters after
that indicate the permissions that are
set for that file so this like we saw
earlier I might not be able to open a
given file or I might not be able to CD
into a given directory and this is all
dictated by the permissions on that
particular file or directory the way to
read these is that the the first group
of three are the permissions are set for
the owner of the file all of these files
you'll see are owned by me the second
group of three characters is for the
permissions for the group that owns this
file in this case all of these files are
also known by the john group and a final
group of three is a list of the
permissions for everyone else so anyone
who's not a user owner or a group owner
this directory is perhaps kind of boring
because all of the things are owned by
me but if we do something like CD to
slash and do LS dash L you'll see that
here all of them are owned by root we'll
get back to what the root user is but
here you see some of the permissions are
a little bit more interesting the groups
of three are read write and execute what
these mean differs for files and for
directories for files it's pretty
straightforward if you have read
permissions on a file then you can read
its contents if you have write
permissions on a file then you can save
the file you can add more to it or you
can replace it entirely and if you have
execute to the X bit on a file then
you're allowed to execute that file so
if we do LS al in slash bin that's a
novel and user bin you'll see that all
of them have the execute bit set even
for people who are not the owner of the
file and this is because the echo
program for example we want everyone on
the computer to be able to execute
there's no reason to say only certain
users can run echo that doesn't really
make any make any sense
for directories though these permissions
are a little bit different so read
translates - are you allowed to see
which files are inside this directory so
think of read as lists for a directory
are you allowed to list its contents
write for a directory is whether you are
allowed to rename create or remove files
within that directory so it's still kind
of right but notice that this means that
if you have write permissions on a file
but you do not have write permissions on
its directory you cannot delete the file
you can empty it but you cannot delete
it because that would require writing to
the directory itself and finally execute
on directories is something that trips
people up a lot execute on a directory
is what's known as search and that's not
terribly helpful a name but what that
means is are you allowed to enter this
directory if you want to get to a file
if you want to open it or read it or
write it whatever you want to do
basically to CD into a directory you
must have the execute permission on all
parent directories of that directory and
the directory itself so for example for
me to access a file inside slash user
slash bin such as user bin echo I must
have executed on route I must have
execute on user and I must have execute
on bin if I do not have all those
execute bits I will not be allowed to
access that file because I won't be able
to enter the directories along the way
there are a number of other bits that
you might come across like you might see
esses or T's in these lists you might
see LS those we can talk about in office
hours if you're curious
they will mostly not matter for anything
you will do in this class but they are
handy to know about so if you're curious
about them look them up on your own or
come ask us in office hours there are
some other programs that are handy to
know about oh sorry there's one more
thing as I mentioned if you just have a
dash it means you do not have that
permission right so if it says for
example our dash X it means that you
have read and execute but you do not
have right there are some other handy
programs to know about at this point
one of them is move or the MV command so
if I CD back to missing semester here MV
lets me rename a file and rename here
takes two paths it takes the old path in
the new path this is means that move
lets you both rename a file like if you
change the name of the file but not the
directory or it lets you move a file to
a completely different directory it just
you give the path to the current file
and the path to where you want that file
to be and that can change its location
and its name so for example I can move
dot files dot MD to be food MD
unhelpfully right and similarly I can
move it back there's also the CP command
the CP or copy is very similar it lets
you copy a file CP also takes two
arguments it takes the path you want to
copy from and the path you want to copy
to and these are full paths so I could
use this for example to say I want to
copy dot files out MD - dot dot slash
food MD sure food MD and now if I do LS
dot you'll see that there's a food MD
file in that directory so CP as well
take two paths it does not have to be in
the same directory and similarly there's
the RM command which lets you remove a
file and there - you can give paths in
this case I'm removing dot dot slash
food you should be aware for removing
especially on Linux removal is by
default not recursive so you cannot
remove a directory using RM you can pass
the - our flag which lets you do a
recursive remove and then give a path
that you want to remove and it will
remove everything below it there is also
the RM dr dir command which lets you
remove a directory but it only lets you
remove that directory if it is empty so
the idea here is to sort of be a safety
mechanism for you so you don't
accidentally throw away a bunch of your
files and the final little command
that's handy to use is make there which
lets you create a new directory and as
we talked about before you don't want to
do something like this because it will
create two directories for you one
called my and one called photos if you
actually want to create a directory like
this you would either
escape the space or quote the string if
you ever want more information about how
any command to basically on these
platforms work there's a really handy
command for that as well
there is the program called man for
manual pages this program takes as an
argument the name of another program and
gives you its manual page so for example
we could do man LS and this shows us a
manual page for LS you'll notice that in
the case of LS it is fairly similar to
what we got with LS - help but it's a
little easier to navigate a little
easier to read usually towards the
bottom you will also get examples
information about who wrote it where you
can find more information and that sort
of stuff one thing that can be confusing
sometimes
at least until a recent version where
they added this three at the bottom
which says Q to quit they do not use to
say this you press Q to quit this
program it can be really hard to quit it
if you do not know that a handy keyboard
shortcut here by the way is ctrl L which
lets you clear your terminal and go back
to the top so so far we've only talked
about programs in isolation but where
much of the power of the shell really
comes through is once you start
combining different programs right so
rather than just like running CDE
running LS and etc you might want to
chain multiple programs together you
might want to interact with files and
have files operate in between programs
and the way we can do this is using this
notion of streams that the shell gives
us every program by default has I'm
gonna simplify a little and say two
primary streams it has an input stream
and an output stream by default the
input stream is your keyboard basically
the input stream is your terminal and
whatever you type into your terminal is
going to end up into the program and it
has a default output stream which is
whenever the program prints something
it's gonna print to that stream and by
default that is also your terminal this
is why when I type echo hello it gets
printed back to my terminal but the
shell gives you a way to rewire these
streams to change where the input
output of a programmer pointed the way
the most straightforward way you do this
is using the angle bracket signs so you
can write something like this or you can
write something like this the left angle
bracket indicates rewire the input for
this program to be the contents of this
file and the end angle bracket means
rewire the output of the preceding
program into this file so let's look at
an example of what that would look like
if I do echo hello I can say I want that
context the content to be stored in a
file called hello dot text and because I
gave this is a relative path right this
will construct a file in the current
directory called hello text and at least
in theory its contents should be the
word hello so if I run this notice that
nothing got printed to my output the
previous time when I ran echo hello it
printed hello
now that hello is going gone into a file
called hello text and I can verify this
by using the program called cat so cat
prints the contents of a file so I can
do cat hello dot txt and there it shows
me hello but cat is a is also something
that supports this kind of wiring so I
can say cat which by default just prints
its input it just duplicates its input
to its output I can say I want you to
take your input from Hello text what
will happen in this case is that the
shell is going to open hello dot txt
take its contents and set that to be the
input of cat and then cat is going to
just print that to its output which
since I haven't rewired it is gonna be
my terminal so this will just print
hello to the output and I can use both
of these at the same time so for example
if I want to copy a file and I don't
want to use the CP command for some
reason I can do this and in this case
I'm telling the cat program nothing at
all I'm just saying do your normal thing
right the cat program does not know
anything about this redirection but I'm
telling the shell to use hello dot txt as
the input for cat and to write anything
that cat prints - hello - dot txt again
this prints nothing to my terminal
but if
cat hello to text I get the output as I
would have expected which is a copy of
the original file there is also a double
end bracket which is append instead of
just overwrite so you'll notice that I
if I do
cat hello dot txt - hello - dot txt
again and then I cat hello2 dot txt it
still just contains hello even though it
already contained hello if I switch that
to instead be a double end bracket it
means append and if I now cat that file
it has a hello twice these are pretty
straightforward they're usually just
ways to interact with files but where it
gets really interesting is an additional
operator the shell gives you called the
pipe character so pipe is just a
vertical bar and what pipe means is take
the output of the program to the left
and make it the input of the program to
the right right so what does this look
like well let's take the example of ls /
or ls dash l / this prints a bunch of
things let's say that I only wanted the
last line of this output well there's a
command called tail and tail prints the
last n lines of its input and I can do
-n1 so this is a flag called n you
can also use dash dash lines if you want
to use it as a longer option but in this
case this is saying just print the last
line and I can wire these together so I
can say ls dash l / pipe tail -n1
and notice here that ls does not know
about tail and tail does not know about
ls they are different programs and have
never been programmed to be compatible
with one another all they know how to do
is read from input and write to output
and then the pipe is what wires them
together and in this particular case I'm
saying I want the output of LS to be the
input to tail and then I want the output
of tail to just go to my terminal
because I haven't rewired it
I could also rewire this to say I want
the output to go to ls dot text and in this
case if I cat ls dot text I would get
the appropriate output and it turns out
you can do some really neat things with this
gonna cover this a lot more in the data
wrangling lecture there will be in like
four days or something on the kind of
fancy stuff you can do when you start
building more advanced pipelines one to
give you one example we can do something
like curl - -head --silent google.com
so just to show you what that looks
like this gives me all the HTTP headers
for accessing google.com and I can pipe
that to grep a - like a --ignore-case
or just -i if I want content
length so this is gonna print the
content length header, grep is a program
that we'll talk about later they'll let
you search in an input stream for a
given keyword we can pipe that through
say the cut command which takes a
delimiter set that to be space and I
want the second field and this prints
just the content length this is sort of
a silly example right like this just
lets you extract the content length in
bytes of google.com from the command
line it's not a very useful thing to do
but you can see how by chaining these
together you can achieve a bunch of
really interesting text manipulation
effects and it turns out pipes are not
just for textual data you can do this
for things like images as well you can
have a program that manipulates a binary
image on its input and writes a binary
image to its output and you can chain
them together in this way and we'll talk
about some of those kinds of examples
later on - you can even do this for
video if you want you can stream this is
for example a great way if you have a
chromecast at home you can stream a
video file like this by having the last
program in your pipe be a chromecast
send program so you stream a video file
into it and it streams or HTTP to your
chromecast we'll take we'll talk a lot
more about this in the data wrangling
lecture but there's one more thing that
I wanted to talk to you about about sort
of how to use the terminal and a more
interesting and perhaps more powerful
way that you might be used to and this
is perhaps even going to be interesting
for the ones of you who feel like you're
already comfortable with the term
but first we need to cover a important
topic when it comes to Linux systems and
Mac OS systems in particular which is
the notion of the root user the root
user is sort of like the administrator
user on Windows and it has user IDs zero
the root user is special because it is
allowed to do whatever it wants on your
system even if a file is like not
readable by anyone or if it's not
writable by anyone root can still access
that file root is sort of a super user
that gets to do whatever they want and
most of the time you will not be
operating as the super user you will not
be root you will be a user like John or
whatever your name is and that's going
to be the user you act with because if
you were operating your computer as the
root user at all times if you ran the
wrong program they could just completely
destroy your computer and you don't want
that right but every now and again you
want to do something that requires that
you are root usually for these cases you
will use a program called sudo su do or
do as su and su in this case is Super
User so this is a way to do the
following thing as the super user
usually the way sudo works is you write
sudo and then a command like you would
normally on your terminal and it will
just run that command as if you were
root as opposed to the user you actually
are where might you need something like
this well there is a special there are
many special file system on your
computer but in particular there's one
called sysfs if you CD to slash sys
this is a whole new world this file
system is are not actually files on your
computer instead these are various
kernel parameters so the kernel is like
basically the the core of your computer
this is a way for you to access various
kernel parameters through what looks
like a file system you'll see here that
if I CD into class for example it has
directories for a bunch of different
types of devices that I can interact
with or various queues I can access or all
sorts of weird knobs internally and
because they're exposed as files it means
we can also use all the tools have been
using so far in order to manipulate them
one example of this is if you go into
sys class backlight so this backlight
directly and lets you configure the
backlight on your laptop if you have one
so I can CD in to intel backlight this
is an Intel laptop inside here you'll
see there's a file called brightness and
I can cat the brightness this is the
current brightness of my screen but not
only that I can modify this too in order
to change the brightness of my screen so
you might think that I could do let's
see what the max brightness is here okay
so it's currently set to the max
brightness you might imagine that I
could do something like if I do echo
let's do half or something
echo 500 to brightness
if I do this it says
permission denied I'm not allowed to
modify brightness because in order to
basically in order to change things in
the kernel you need to be the
administrator and you might imagine that
the way to solve this is to write sudo
echo 500 but I still get a permission
denied error but why is that it's
because as I mentioned before these
redirections of input and output is not
something the programs know about when
we piped Elison to tail tail did not
know about LS and LS did not know about
tail the pipe and the redirection was
set up by the shell so in this case
what's happening is I'm telling my shell
run the program sudo with the arguments
echo and 500 and send its output to the
file called brightness but the shell is
what is opening the brightness file it
is not the sudo program so in this case
the shell which is running as me tries
to open the brightness file for writing
and it's not allowed to do that and
therefore I get a permission down error
you might have seen this if you like
search for something end up on Stack
Overflow and it tells just run this
command and you'll see that it does
something like they give you
instructions like one two sis what's an
example net ipv4 for word for example
this is something you may have seen if
you're setting up a firewall and this
command is intended to work
because this little pound symbol
indicates run this as root this is
something that is very rarely explained
but that is what the pound symbol means
you'll see on my prompt there's a dollar
symbol instead and the dollar indicates
you are not running as root so the
question is how do I get around this
well I could switch into a root terminal
so one way to do this is to run sudo su
sudo su is saying run the following
command s root and su is a complicated
command that effectively gets you a
shell as the super user so if I do this
type of password then now you'll see
that the username at the beginning
changed from jon to root and the prompt
changed from a dollar to a pound if I
now I come in to that file if I do echo
500 to brightness my screen got a little
dimmer but you can't see it you just
have to trust me and now I didn't get an
error and this is because the shell is
now running as root it is not running as
Jon and the root user is allowed to open
this file but given our knowledge that
we have of the terminal now there's
actually a way for us to do this without
having to drop to a root shell and that
is as follows that's I guess restore it
to 1060 so do you see why this is
different here I'm telling my shell to
run the echo 1060 command which is gonna
echo 1060 and I'm telling it to run the
sudo tee brightness command and I'm
telling you to send the output of echo
into sudo tee in order to understand this
you need to know what the tee command does
the tee command takes its input and writes
it to a file but also to standard out so
tee is a convenient way if you have say a
log file that you want to like send to a
file to store for later but you also
want to see it to yourself then you can
pipe it through tee give it the name of a
file and it will write whatever its
input is both to that file and to your
screen and here I'm taking advantage of
that program I'm saying run tee as route
and have tee right into the brightness
file and so in this case the tee program
which is what is opening the brightness
file is running as root and so it is
allowed to do
if I run this it will now again you
can't see but the brightness and I've
been turned on by a laptop and I don't
get any errors and I never had to drop
into a root shell and run commands there
which can often be somewhat dangerous if
you want to explore this filesystem a
little bit more there's a lot of
interesting stuff in here if you just
sort of start browsing around you can
find all sorts of fun things so for
example we noticed that there was a fun
brightness command here I wonder what
other kinds of brightness I can set so I
can use the find command which we will
also talk about in a coming lecture I
wouldn't look on any file whose name
it's a little like brightness in the
current directory that's unhelpful maybe
they're not files did I misspell
brightness yeah why is it being annoying
Oh apparently it does not want to search
for brightness for me how well luckily
for you I know of one already handy that
there is a subdirectory called LEDs and
LEDs have brightness too what kind of
LEDs are there ooh lots of things for
example the scroll lock led now most of
you probably don't know what the scroll
lock LED is or much less what scroll
lock is you might have seen a key on
your keyboard neighbor named scroll lock
basically no one knows what it means
anymore no one really uses it for
anything it's mostly just a dead key and
also a dead LED what if you wanted to
configure it so that every time you get
email your scroll lock LED lights up
because there's no other reason why it
would light up well if we seed you into
this particular directory that has a
brightness place and it's set to zero
well what happens if I write one into it
you probably should not just be writing
random numbers into random files in this
directory because you are affecting your
kernel directly like look up what the
files do in this particular case I have
warned safety goggles and I've done my
research so now you can't tell but on my
keyboard the scroll lock LED is now lit
so now if I wrote a program that like
did some checking of mail and stuff I
could have it at the end run a program
that echoes one into this file and now I
have a way for my led to my keyboard to
indicate when I've new email at this
point you should know roughly your way
around
the terminal around the shell and and
know enough to accomplish these basic
tasks at least in theory now you
shouldn't need to use like
point-and-click interfaces to find files
anymore
there's one remaining trick you might
need and that is the ability to open a
file so far I've only really given you
ways to find files but one thing you
should know about is missing semester
xdg-open this will probably only work
on Linux on Mac OS I think it's just
called open on Windows who knows
xdg-open you give the name of a file and
it will open it in the appropriate program
so if you open if you do xdg-open an
HTML file that will open your browser
and open that file and once you have
that program in theory you should no
longer need to open like a Finder window
ever again you might want to for other
reasons but in theory you can accomplish
at all using the tools that we've
learned today this might all seem
relatively basic for some of you but as
I mentioned this is sort of the ramp-up
period of now we all know how the shell
works and a lot of what we'll be doing
in future lectures is using this
knowledge to do really interesting
things using the shell that sort of this
is learning the the interface that we're
going to be using and so it's important
we all know it we're gonna talk a lot
more in the next lecture about how to
automate tasks like this how to write
scripts that run a bunch of programs for
you and have to do things like
conditionals and loops and stuff in your
terminal and do things like run a
program until it fails which can be
handy in classes where you want to run
something until your test suite fails
for example so that's the topic for next
week's lecture did you have a question
it's what you've been demoing this
assist directory that presumably will
only work if you're running that is a
good question I don't know whether the
windows subsystem for Linux will expose
the sis file system if it does it
probably only exposes a very small
number of things it might because there
are I don't know check it out
one thing you'll see is the lecture
notes for this lecture are already
online and at the very bottom of the
file there are a bunch of exercises some
of them are relatively easy some of them
are a little bit harder and what we
encourage you to do is to take a stab at
going through them if you know this
stuff already it should go really
quickly if you don't it might teach you
a bunch of things that you might not
realize you didn't know and for the
office hours that we're gonna do right
after this lecture we will happily help
you get through all of those or if there
are other commands and you learn in the
process you want to know how to use more
efficiently and then in next lecture
which is tomorrow will basically be
assuming that you know the kind of stuff
that the exercise is going to teach you
there's also a an email address on the
website where you can send us questions
if you think of something like after the
office hours are finished are there any
questions before we end today no no all
right well we will have office hours on
the ninth floor of the gates building of
building 32 in like five minutes
sweet see you there