No okay welcome back and today we're
gonna cover kind of a couple separate
like two main topics straight to the
cell first we're gonna do some kind of
cell scripting mainly related to bass
which is like this a lot most of you
will start and like in Mack like like
most Linux systems as the beef also and
it's also kind of backward compatible
through other souls like see see it's
pretty nice and then we're gonna cover
some kind of or sell tools that are
really convenient when you're boy doing
like really repetitive tasks like
looking for some piece of code them for
some elusive file a and there are very
kind of really nice built-in comments
that will it kind of really help help
you to do those things and so this
territory kind of introduce you to the
cell and like kind of like some of its
quirks sound like how you're executing
commands reacting them it they're gonna
kind of cover more about like the syntax
of where like the bible's the control
flow functions of set so for example
ones you're kind of drop into a cell say
you want to kind of define a variable
which is kind of kind of like one of the
first things you learn to do in a in a
primary language here you could do
something like foo equals bar and now we
can access the value of foo by doing
dollar food and that's
bar perfect a one quick that you need to
be aware is that like spaces are really
critical when you're dealing with bus
mainly because spaces reserved and that
will be for separating arguments so for
example something like foo equals bar
won't work and the the in the soil is
gonna tell you why is no work is because
the food common is not working like if
food is not exist and here where it's
actually happening we're not assigning
food to are what is happening we're
calling the full program with the first
argument equal sign and the second
argument bar and in general whenever you
are having some issues some like some
files with the spaces we do need to be
careful about that about you you need to
be careful about like coding strings
that so going into that how you do is
strings in bus there are two ways that
you can define a string you can define
strings using double quotes and you can
define strings using single editor using
single quotes a however for literal
strings they are equivalent but for the
rest they are not equal so for example
if we do equals dollar value is dollar
full the dollar foo is has been kind of
like expanded like strings to delete to
the value of the full variable in the
cell whereas if we do this with a simple
string we are just getting the dollar
foo as it is unlike single quotes won't
be replacing and again it's really easy
to kind of write a scrip assume that
this is kind of like Python that you
might be more familiar with and not
realize all that and this is the way you
will assign variables then a bass or
walk like control flow techniques that
we later like for loops while loops and
the only thing is you can define
functions and a we can access like a
function they have define here and here
we have the MCD function has been
defined and the thing is so far we have
just kind of seen how to execute several
comments by piping in to them kind of
saw that briefly yesterday but a lot of
times you want to do where is one thing
and then another thing and that's kind
of like the the sequential execution
that we get here here for example we're
calling the MCD function and we first
are calling it with the make their
common which is like creating dessert
tree a heat baller one is like a special
viral and this is the way that bus works
whereas in other scripting languages
that will be like are to be the first
the first item of the array are the V we
contain the argument in passes dollar
one and you know a lot of things in bars
will be dollar something and will be
reserved we will be seeing more examples
later and
we have created the folder we CD into
the into that folder which is kind of
like a very common parent that you will
see we will actually type this directly
into our soul and it will work and it
will define this function but sometimes
is nicer to kind of grab things in the
file and what we can do is we can source
this and I will execute this script in
your soul and load it so now it looks
like nothing happened but now the NCD
function has been defined in torso so we
can now some people do like MCD test and
now we move from the tools directory to
the test directory we both like we
created the the folder and we move into
it what else so I'm a result is like we
can access we access the first argument
with dollar one there's a lot more kind
of reserved comments for example door
zero will be the name of the script
there are two to three dollar nine will
be the second through the ninth
arguments that the word script takes
some of these reserved keywords are more
and also kind of be reggae use in the
cells for example dollar interrogation
mark we get you the error code from the
previous common a and which I will also
explain briefly but for example dollar
underscore will get you the last
argument of the previous comment so
another way we will have done the issues
we will have say like egg came a little
test and instead of kind of rewriting
test we can access that last argument as
part of the using the dollar dollar
underscore like that will be replaced
with test and now we go into tests in
there are a lot of them this will kind
of familiarize with them another one I
often use is kind of it's called bang
bang you will run into this whenever you
for example are trying to create
something and you don't have enough
permissions then you can do suit
bang-bang and then that will replace the
common in there and now you can just try
doing that and now it will prompt you
for password because you have sudo
permission um before I mentioned the
kind of the error command yesterday we
saw that in general there are like
different ways a process can communicate
with kind of all our processes or
comments we mentioned the standard input
which was it was like the less than like
getting stuff through this entire input
getting putting stuff into the standard
output there are kind of a couple more
interesting things it's also like a
standard error a stream where you kind
of write errors that happen with your
program and you want to pollute the
Easterner output it's also the error
code which is kind of like a general
thing in other foreign languages of like
some kind of way of reporting how the
entire run of something when so if we do
something like echo hello and we like
wait for the value is zero and it's here
because everything went okay anyone
where any issues and a zero exit code is
the same as you will get in a language
like C like Cu means everything went
fine there are no errors however
sometimes things won't work like
sometimes like we try to grab for fubar
in or or MCD Script and now we check for
the value is one and that's because we
try to search for a fuller string in the
MCD script and it wasn't there
so like the grep doesn't bring anything
but lets us know the things didn't work
by giving us like a one error code and
there are some interesting comments like
true for example we always have zero
error code and false will always have
one error code and then there are like
these logical operators that you can use
to do some sort of like conditionals for
example one way you also have ifs
analysis that will clear but you can do
something like false and oops fail so
here we have to come
connected by this or appear what boss is
gonna do here is gonna execute the first
one and if the first one being working
just gonna execute the second one so
here we get it because the like it's
gonna try to do the logical or if the
first one didn't have a serial called in
is gonna try to do the second one
similarly if we instead of use false we
use something like true since true will
have a serial code then the second one
will be short circuit and we don't it
won't be printed similarly we have an an
operator which will only execute the
second part if the first one like run
without errors and this same thing will
happen if the first one fails then the
second part of this demon won't be
executed a kind of not exactly ready to
that but another thing that you will see
is that no matter what you execute then
you can concatenate commands using a
semicolon in the same line and that will
always spread beyond what we haven't
seen for example is how will you go
about doing kind of getting the output
of a common into a viable and the way we
can do that is doing something like this
where what we're doing here is we're
getting the output of the PWD comment
which is just printing the present
working directory where we are right now
and then we're storing that into the
full bio so we do that and then we as
for full we were string and more
generally we can do this thing called
common substitution or but putting it
into any string and since we're using
like double quotes instead of single
quotes the thing will be expanded and it
will tell us that m we are in this
working folio a another interesting
thing is right now what
this is expanding this to a string
instead of kind of like M this is the
spending as a string underneath T and
like lesser known tool is called process
substitution which is kind of similar
where we will do and it will hear for
example the less than parenthesis some
command and another parenthesis that
will do is that will execute that will
get the output to kind of like a
temporary file and you will give the
file handle to the common so here what
we're doing is we're getting where LS in
the directory cannot put it into a
temporary file doing the same thing for
the pine folder and then we're
concatenating both files and this we
might be really handy because some
comments instead of expecting the input
coming from the STD in they are
expecting things to come from some file
that is giving some of the arguments so
we get kind of both things concatenated
a thing like so further has been a lot
of information let's see kind of like a
simple like an example X script where we
see a few of these things so sample here
we're having like a string and we have
kind of this door date don't date is a
program so again there's a lot of
programs in UNIX you will kind of slowly
familiarize with a lot of them they just
prints a what the current date is and
you can specify different formats a then
we have these doors here here Toller CU
is the name of the script that we're
running then we have bowler has does the
number of arguments that we are giving
to the common and then dollar dollar is
the process ID of this common dairies
front again there's a lot of kind of
these dollar things they're not
intuitive because they don't have like a
mnemonic way of remember if maybe torah
has but it can be you just kind of have
really seen them and get familiar with
it
here we have this dollar at and that
will expand to all the arguments so
instead of having to assume that may
say we have three arguments and ready in
dollar one or two or three if we don't
know how many arguments we can put all
those arguments there and that has been
given to like a four and the four loop
will in time get like the file viable
and it will kind of be given it's one of
the arguments so what we're doing is for
every one of the arguments were given
then in the next line we are running the
grep common which is search for a
substring in some file and we're
searching for the string fubar
in the file here we have kind of put the
variables of the file to expand and
yesterday we saw the like if we care
about the output of a program we can
redirect it to somewhere to save it or
like to connect it to some other file
key but sometimes you want the opposite
sometimes here for example we care we're
going to care about the error code about
this script we're going to care whether
the crap run successfully or it didn't
so we can actually be scarred and
tiredly what the output like both the
standard output and standard error of
the grab comma and what we're doing is
we're redirecting the output to deafen
all which is kind of like a special
device in in UNIX systems where you can
like write and it won't it will be
discarded like you can drive no matter
how much you want to there and it will
be discarded and here's the kind of the
grate and our symbol that we should just
tell you for project in the output here
you have like a to greater than and as
some of you might have guessed by now
this is for erecting the standard error
because those those two streams are
separate and you can have to tell bus
what to do with each one okay so here we
run with check if the file has fuller
and if the file has fewer than it's
going to have a serial code if it
doesn't have four words gonna have a
non-spherical
so that's actually what we check in this
if part of the common we say get me the
error code again this dollar question
mark
and then we have a comparison operator
which is an e for not equals unlike some
other primal images we do have kind of
like equals equals behind equals these
symbols in Bath's they're like kind of
like a reserved set of comparisons and
it's mainly because there's a lot of
things you might want to test for when
you're in the cell here for example
we're just taking probably two values to
into your values being the same or for
example here the minus F check will let
us know if a file exists which is
something that you will run into very
very commonly I'm going back to the
example then what happens when we what
happens when we go into if the file did
not have fubar like there was like an
nonzero error code then we print like
this file doesn't happen if we were
we're going to add one and what we do is
we echo this like has four hoping this
is a comment to the file and then we're
using the privacy of like greater
gradient to append at the end of the
file and here since the file is has been
fed through the script and we don't know
beforehand we have to substitute the
Bible of the filename a we can actually
run this we already have like correct
permissions in this script and we can
give a few example you have like a few
files in this folder and CD is the one
we we saw the beginning for the MC
function like some script function and
we can even feed it the own like script
to itself to check that like it has four
in it and we run it and we first we can
see that like this different like
variables that we saw that we have been
successfully expanded we have date has
been replaced to the current time then
were running this program with three
arguments this random and PD and then is
telling us om CD doesn't have any fours
we are having a new
and this the business profile doesn't
have one so now for example look sue MCD
has big comment that we were looking for
and one other thing to know when you're
kind of executing these scripts is that
here we have like three completely
different arguments but very commonly
you will be given like arguments that
can be more succinctly given in some way
so for example here if we wanted to
refer to all the dot s8 scripts we will
just do something like less asterisk
Doris aids and this is a way of kind of
finding expansion that most cells have
is called gloving and here as you might
expect this is gonna say Oh
anything that has any kind of sort of
characters and end up with effects so
unsurprisingly we get kind of example
estate and insidious AIDS we also have
this project one and predict - and if
they were like we can do like a project
for it - for example more and now if we
just want to refer to the prey that have
a single character but not two
characters at the wall so like any other
character we can use the question mark
so question mark will expand to only a
single one and we get like enough where
LS in first pretty one and then a
project - they're all kind of like the
globe in can be very powerful you can
also kind of combine it a the a common
pattern is to use what is called curly
braces so let's say we have an image now
we have in this folder and we want to
convert this image from PNG to jpg or we
call it maybe like copy it or it's like
Greek common peroneal have two more
arguments are fairly similar and you
want to do something about something
with them as arguments to some common
you could do it this way or more
succinctly you can just do in
the open curly bracket then PNG jpg and
hearing it and getting kind of some
color feedback about what this will do
is click expand into the line above and
actually can like a cease it to do that
for me and that what's happening here
this is really powerful so for example
you can do something like we will do
that's unlike a bunch of fools and all
of these will be expanded you can also
do it at several levels and you will do
the Cartesian yeah we have something
like this a we have one group here that
is like one comma two and then here is
like one two three and this is going to
do kind of the Cartesian product of
these two expansions and it will expand
into all these things that we can
quickly touch you can also combine the
asterisk Club with the curly braces Club
you can even use kind of ranges of like
we can do like MKV you and we create the
full and there were directories and then
we can do something along these lines
this is going to expand to full a full
be like all these commissions through J
and then the same for bar like and
haven't really tested budget like we're
getting all these combinations that we
can touch and now if we touch something
there is different between these two we
can again so case the these subtle the
the process substitution that we saw
earlier say we want to kind of check
what files are different between these
two folders for us it's obvious video
soil because is x and y but we can ask
the cell to do this diff for us between
the output of one LS on your LS and of
unsurprisingly we're getting like X is
only in the first folder and why
only in the second polar what is more is
right now the the have fun kind of seen
baskets if you like other scripts like
for some task bus it's probably not best
it can be tricky you can actually read
scripts the interact with the cell
implement in a lot of different
languages so example let's see here
Python script you have a magic line at
the beginning that not explained it for
now then we have like import sis it's
kind of like the Python it's kind of not
by default trying to interact with the
cell so you will have to import some
library and then we're doing a really
silly thing of just iterating over this
cyst or art va1 semicolon which is door
art v is kind of similar to what
embossed we were getting us like the
dollar zero dollar one etc Sara it's
like the factor of the arguments we're
fading we're printing in in the reverse
order and the magic line at the
beginning is called a Steven and is the
way that the cell will know how to run
this program like you can always do
something like a Python script and then
like ABC and that will work like I
always like that but what if we want to
make this to be executable from the cell
the way the cell knows that it has to
use Python as interpreter to run this
file is using that the first line and
first line is giving it kind of the path
to where duckling lips
a-alright you mind not not like
different scenes will have probably
different places where they put Python
and you might not want to assume where
pythons install or any other interpreter
so one thing that you can do is use the
end comment so it's done you cannot you
can also give arguments in this event so
what we're doing here is specifying our
run the end comment that is for pretty
much every
system electronic system but like for
pretty much every system is called is in
user bin where a lot of binaries live
and then we're calling it with the
argument Python and then that we make
use of the a path environment variable
that we saw in the first lecture it's
gonna search in that pub for thee by the
memory and then is gonna use that to
interpret this file and that will make
this more portable so they can be run in
my machine and your machine and some
orbs another thing is that the bus lag
is not really like more than how big it
was developed a while ago and sometimes
think a bit tricky to debug and like by
default the the the waste will fail
sometimes are intuitive like the way we
saw before of like foo common not
existing sometimes is not so there's
like really nifty tool that we have
linked in the electro node which cold
salt tech that will kind of give you
both warnings and like syntactic errors
sort of things that you might not have
or it properly
I might misfire you have like a spaces
in your files so for example for
extremely simple em City I say it's file
we're getting a couple of furs saying
like hey so presently we're missing a
statement like this minor interpret
correctly if you're running the
different system also this CD is taking
a common and it might not expand
properly so instead of using CD you
might want to use something like CD and
then an or and then an exit we go back
to what we explained earlier what this
is what this will do is like if the CD
doesn't end correctly you cannot see D
into the folder because either you don't
have permissions doesn't exist that we
give an on C like a nonce your error in
common so you will execute exit and I
will like a stop the script instead of
like continue executing assuming you're
in that place that you are actually not
it
and I could have interested but the I
think we can check for the example set
and here we're getting that we still be
you see we should be checking the exit
code in a different way because it's
probably not the best way doing this way
hey one last remark I want to make is
that when the robust scripts they're
like oh like functions for them where
this kind of like a difference between
writing bass scripts in isolation like a
finger you're gonna run I think they're
you're gonna load into yourself we will
see some of this in the common line
environment lecture where we kind of be
tooling with the bass RC and the CC hrc
but you know the if you make changes to
for example where you are like if you CD
into app a script and you just execute
the bus trip it won't CD into the cell
WR right now but if you have loaded the
code directly into yourself for example
we loaded these we source the function
and then you execute the function then
you will get those side effects and the
same goes for defining variables into
the cell and now I'm gonna kind of talk
about some tools there are things like
committee when working with the solo if
the first we was also briefly introduced
yesterday how do you know like what
flags or like what except comments can
do like how I am supposed to know the
like LS minus L less the files in a list
format of like if I do move - I it's
gonna like prom me for stuff that what
you have is the man command and the man
command we kind of have like a lot of
information of how will you go about so
for example here we will explain for the
- I flag there are all these options you
can do and that's actually pretty useful
and it will work not only for kind of
really simple comments that kind of
compact it with your OS but will also
work with some
tools that you install from the internet
for example if the person that did the
installation I made it so that the man
pages were also installed so for example
of tools that were gonna cover in an a
bit which is called brick brick brick
rep and is call with Rd like this didn't
come with my system but it has installed
its own man page and I have it here and
I can access it a for some comments the
man page is useful but sometimes can be
tricky to decipher because it's more
kind of like a documentation and a
description of all the things the fool
can do but not sometimes it will have
example but sometimes not and sometimes
the tool can do a lot of things so a a
couple of good tools that I use commonly
are combat or ffs mpg which deal with
images and video respectively and the
Muppets are like enormous so it's like
one neat tool called the ldr that you
can install and it will have like some
nice kind of explanatory examples of how
you want to use this comma and you can
always Google for this but I find myself
saving like going into the browser
looking about some examples and coming
back where like the earlier are like
kind of community contributed and they
they're like figley useful then like the
the one for FM Vee has a lot of useful
examples are like more nicely formatted
if you don't have like a huge font size
for recording a poor even simple
commands like tired I have a lot of
options that you are combining so for
example here you can be combined into
three different flags and cannot be
obvious when you want to combine
different ones that's how you kind of
will go about kind of finding more about
these tools a topic of finding let's try
using how to find fast like you can
always go less unlike we can go like
last project one and
keep a lesson all the way through but
maybe where we already know that we want
to look for all the folders called
SRC then this is probably a bit common
for doing that and that's fine like fine
stool the prima comes if every UNIX
system and find we're gonna give it the
here we're saying we want to call find
in the current folder
remember that dot stands for the current
folder and we want the name to be
searched and we want the type to be a
directory and by typing that is gonna
recursively go through the current
directory and look for all these files
of folders in this case that match this
part and fine has like a lot of useful
flux so for example you can even test
for the path to be in a way here we're
saying oh we want some number of folders
we don't really care that many folders
and then we care about all the python
script like all the things with the
extension dot pi they are within a
tasteful and we also check in just in
cases recently but we're checking just
that is also a type F which stands for
five and we're getting all these files a
you can also use different flags for
thing they are not like the path or the
name you could check things that have
been modified like m time is for like
the modification time things that have
been modified in the last day which is
gonna be pretty much everything is gonna
print a lot of the files we create and
files that were already there and you
can even use all things like size the
owner permissions you name what is even
more powerful is fine can kind of find
stuff but it also can do stuff when
would you find those files so we could
look for all the files and a half like a
TMP extension which is like a temporary
extension and
we can't find that like for every one of
those files just execute the RM common
for them and that will just be calling
RM with all these files so let's first
execute it without and then we execute
it with it again as we like the common
line philosophy it looks like nothing
happened but since we have non zero
sorry I see your error code something
happen it's just like everything when
correct and everything is fine and now
if we look for these files they're in
there anymore
I know nice thing about BA about the
selling journal is that like there are
like these tools but people will keep
finding new ways or like alternative
ways of writing these tools and it's
kind of nice to know about it so for
example find if you just want to match
like the last like the things up and in
TMP can be sometimes weird to do this
thing like it has like a long common and
there is like things that I get thee for
example there is like a sorter comment
that by default we used frag X and you
will ignore your get file so you don't
like search even for them and it will
color code it will have like a barrier
Unicode support it's like nice to know
about some of these tools but again the
main idea is that in if you are aware
that these tools exist you can save
yourself a lot of time from doing kind
of menial and repetitive tasks another
comment to bear in mind is like fine
like for some of you may be wondering
like fine is probably yes it's actually
going through directory structure and
looking for the things but what if I'm
doing a lot of fine so they wouldn't be
better doing kind of like a database
approach and like build an index first
and then use the index and update it in
some way well actually most most UNIX
systems already do and this is through
the locate
comment and the way that the locate you
will
we usually will just look for paths in
your file system that have the substring
the york and i actually didn't know if
it will work okay working let me try to
do something like missing semester
you're gonna take awhile but the
suddenly like you found all these file
there are somewhere in my file system
and in the house like built and index
already on them is much faster and then
to like keep in a daily decision like
the update vbe comment that it is
running through cron to update this
database a finding files again is like
really useful sometimes you're actually
concerned about not the files themselves
but the content of the files for that
you can use the grep command that we
have seen so far so you can do something
like grep for in MCD is there what if
you want to again like find recursive
search through the current structure and
look for more files right like we don't
want to do this manually we produce fine
and the exact but actually grab has like
the minus capital r flag that will go
through the entire a directory here and
it's telling us that oh we have the four
line in example a sites of these three
places and in this or two places in for
a it this can be really convenient when
mainly kind of the use case for this is
you know you have written some code in
some like prime languages and you know
it's somewhere in your file system but
you actually don't know but you can
actually quickly search so for example i
can quickly search for all the Python
files that I have in my scratch folder
where I use the like request library
and if I run this like it's giving me
like through all these files exactly
what line it has been found and here
instead of using grep which is fine like
you could also do this I'm using Riblet
which is a kind of like the same idea
but again trying to bring some more
niceties like color coding or file
processing and all things like has also
very unicode support has it's also
pretty fast we are not playing like a
trade-off unlike this being slower and
there's a lot of useful Flags like you
can say oh I actually want to get some
context around those results know if it
committed so yes so I want to get like
five lines of context around that so you
can say like see where that import lists
and see kind of go around it here in the
import isn't really useful but like if
you are looking for where you use the
function for example a it will be it's
pretty handy we can also do things like
a we can see it for example here some
like a more advanced use we can say is
you is for like don don ignore like
hidden files a sometimes that that can
be then like you would tell me you want
to be knowing a hidden file ciphers you
want shirt config files of that that
like by default hidden then instead of
printing the matches we're asking to do
something that will be kind of hard I
think to do with grep out of like my
head which is I want you to print all
the files that don't match the partner
giving you which may be a weird thing to
ask you but then we keep going and this
parent here is like a small red X which
is saying no the beginning of the line I
have a house and a bang and that's a
seeming like that we're searching here
for all the files that don't I don't
have a seat and then we're giving it
like here like am
t-minus aside to only look for like a
sights files because maybe you're like
all your all your Python or text files
are fine we felt like a sieve and here
is telling us all like McD's obviously
missing as even a we can even they have
like some also tonight's flag so for
example if we include the status flag
I don't read actually it will get all
these colleges also but it will also
tell us like information about like all
the things that I searched for example
like the number of mats the matches that
I found max lines the file died certs
the writer printed etc a similar as with
every sometimes is not as useful mmm
using one specific tool or another and
in fact as regrip there are like several
other tools like AK easy or you know
kind of grep alternative that was
written it was like the silver searcher
ad it was another one and they're all
pretty much interchangeable so like
maybe you're a system that has one or
not the other just knowing that you can
use these things with these tools can be
pretty useful lastly I want to cover
kind of how you go about not finding
files or code but how do you go about
finding comments that you already sound
something like figure out and the first
obvious way is just using the up arrow
unlikely slowly going through all your
history like looking for these matches
this is actually not very efficient as
you probably guess so the bass has ways
to do this more easily there's the
history common that will bring your
history here I mean CCH and only prints
some of my history but if I say I want
you to print everything from the
beginning of time it will print
everything from the winning of whoever
this history is and since this is a lot
of results
maybe we care about the ones where we
use the combat command to go from some
type of file to some other type of file
so image sorry then we're getting all
this results here about like only ones
that like mats this substrate what what
else would be even more the pyramids all
cells before we link control our who's
like a cave I need to do like backward
shirts and here we have like backward
shirts where we can like type convert
and it's finding the common that we just
type and if we just keep hitting like
controller it will kind of go through
these matches and one like it will let
us like react secure it in in place and
another thing that you can do relate to
that is you can use this really nifty
tool called FC F which is like a fuzzy
finder like you will let you let's say
it will let you do kind of like an
interactive grep and we could do for
example days where we can cut or example
is sh command now all printer to the
standard output and then we can pipe it
through FCF and you just get in all the
lines and then we can interactively kind
of look for the string that we care
about and the nice thing about f c/f is
that if you enable the default bindings
will bind to your controller cell
execution and now you can quickly and
dynamically like look for all the times
you try to combat of Oregon in your
history and it's also like fuzzy
matching whereas like by default grab
all these things you cannot have to
write a reg X like some expression that
we mad with in here here I'm just typing
in combat on ficon and it's just trying
to do the best scan doing the match in
the lines it has a lastly I have told
that probably you have already seen that
I've been using for not retyping this
extremely long commands is this history
substring search where the as I type in
my cell and both F fail to mention but
both base which I think was really
introduced this concept and CCH has a
really nice implementation
we'll let you do is as you type the
common it will dynamically like shirts
back in your history to the same command
I have like a common prefix and then if
you like it will change thus the match
list stops working and then as you do
like the right arrow you can like select
that comment and then like three execute
it I've seen I want to stop a thing I
have a few minutes left so I'm gonna
cover and kind of a couple of tools to
do kind of really quick directory
listing on directories navigation so you
can always use the - are two kind of
like recursively list of some directory
structure but that can be like
suboptimal like I cannot really make
sense of this easily a there's like a
code tool called tree I will be like
like the Matt more like friendly formal
like brain all the staff they will also
color code based on here for example who
is blue because it's a directory and
like this is red because has execute
permissions but we can go even further
than that they're like really nice tools
like a recent one called brute that will
do the same thing but here for example
instead of doing this thing of listing
every single file for example in by we
have this a through J files it will say
out there like more unlisted here and I
can actually start typing and it will
again facili Matt's to the files that
are there and I can quickly select them
and navigate to do them so again it's
good to know that you're not like that
these things exist so you don't lose
unlike lots amount of time like going
for this five um there are also I think
install also like something more similar
to what we will expect your AOS to have
like now Toulouse or like one of like
the max finder that have like an
interactive input where you can just
like use your navigation arrows and
quickly explore it might be overkill but
you'll be surprised how quickly you can
make sense of some directory structure
but just like navigating through it and
pretty much all of these tools will let
you edit like copy files if you just
like look for the options for them a
last addendum is kind of going places
like we have CD and CD it's not like you
will give you two eller's places but
it's pretty handy if you can like
quickly go places you are either you
have been recently or that you go
frequently and you can do this in many
ways there's probably you can start
thinking oh I can make bookmarks I can
make like I can make aliases in the cell
that we will cover at some point a sim
links but but this point like like
programmers have like built all these
tools so the promise have already figure
out a really nice way of doing this and
one way of doing this is using what is
called Auto Jam which person is not
loaded here this is concerning
okay yeah no don't worry I will correct
in the common line environment I don't
know where isn't always well I think
it's because I'd be say well be the
controller and that also exit a fact
that other parts of the script thing at
this point if anyone has any questions
they're like relate to this I'll be more
than happy to answer them if anything
was left unclear otherwise a there's
like a bunch of exercises that we're all
kind of touching on these topics and we
encourage you to kind of try them and
come to office hours where we can help
you kind of figure out how to do them or
like some like bass quakes they are not
there